[Music]
Stanford
University well I don't know should we
go over again the basic construction of
a simple Quantum
field why
not it's not exactly what I have written
here but we can do it
again not again but maybe slightly
different yeah we're ready
okay
so as I
said the trick of introducing
fields from particles see you can go two
ways you can go two ways you can start
with particles and reconstruct why
they're described by fields or you can
start with fields and then work down to
why fields are described by particles or
why Fields um
waves wave
Fields have quanta go either way and
we'll go both ways but we started by
starting with
particles and we said look that's fine
to be talking about one particle or two
particles or three
particles a fixed number of
particles but GE why not try to study
all possible numbers of particles and by
particles now I'm speaking about a
single species of
particle we can come later tonight what
happens if you have more than one
species but but for the moment one kind
of particle and only one kind of
particle
uh let's make a theory in which we can
simultaneously in one Fell Swoop so to
speak uh talk about any number of
particles and all the things that
multiple particles can do and including
situations where the number of particles
change now why would be ever be led to
that
well in Real Life numbers of particles
change the number of photons in this
room is constantly changing they're
being emitted by the electric light
bulbs
um in other contexts particles Decay
turning into other kinds of
particles uh
the neutron can Decay into a
proton an electron and a neutrino and in
the process the number of neutrons
changes the number of protons change
number of electrons number of neutrinos
and in fact the total number of
particles
change so however we have to think about
particles we have to think not only
about the quantum mechanics of a fixed
number of them we we have to think of
that number as changeable so we need a
flexible enough tool to be studying what
happens a single quantum mechanics which
Embraces essentially any number of
particles and even changing number of
particles that's what um that's what the
point is and that's what the point of
inventing Fields is all right any
questions about that and I'll go over it
again since it's a the mathematics is
not is not hard hard but it's know it's
abstract it's abstract and face it we're
not
um we're not as young as we used to be
for one thing um none of
us the mind uh is not necessarily
attuned instantly to orthogonal
functions and um and all that kind of
thing and so it's good to go slow I
rather you learn something rather than
nothing okay so it's very easy to to
learn nothing it's little harder to
learn something okay so we start with
single particle quantum mechanics single
particle description of one single
particle Quantum
mechanically that means that we have
state vectors but State vectors for one
particle we have wave functions for for
those
particles if we have a state of a single
particle let's call it SII little
SII little SII will also stand for its
wave function if we have a state Vector
for a single particle then the wave
function is just the inner product of
the state Vector with a particle at
position X so a state labeled X means a
particle at point x
the state s means some General State but
of a single
particle and that's called s of X what
do you do with it here's a
formula s star of
X Time s of x
and these are wave functions now these
are not Quantum Fields when I go to
Quantum Fields I will use large
capitalized letters even if they happen
to be the same as
this what is that object what does that
correspond to that's the probability to
find the particle at X it's the
probability density the probability
density to find the particle at X all
right probability density prob
dense you can fill in the rest of the
letters a fact about the probability
density is that when you integrate it
over position what do you
get you get
one it happens in this case that one
happens to be the number of particles
isn't it so you get one but you could
also say you get the number of particles
well that's not very interesting because
we only had one partic to begin with and
we're doing one particle quantum
mechanics nevertheless it's a true
fact okay now we next introduced a
collection of one particle states that
formed a basis an orthonormal orthogonal
basis and we can do that in a number of
ways first of all the X States
themselves are orthogonal to each
other and they former basis we'll come
back to that in a
minute but there are many many ways of
choosing
bases essentially you take the igen
vectors of any Herm Mission operator
will form a basis and in particular if
we're interested we may be especially
interested in energy IG States for
example of a particle in a box that
represents a box the horizontal axis is
the position the vertical axis is the
potential energy
when you get to the edge of the Box the
potential energy becomes huge and the
particle just reflects off it can't get
through and that case the ground state
wave function looks like that the first
and we'll call that s 1 of
X the next energy ion state looks like
that we'll call it S 2 of X and these
are basically signs sign of uh you know
there
two nodes and they're characterized by
the number of
nodes uh rather peculiarly I started
with s one which has no nodes S 2 has
one node but so be
it s i
ofx and since these are supposed to be
energy igen States they're orthogonal to
each other they form an orthonormal
basis so let's write the equation for
that the equation for that is that
integral of
s star I of
X with s j of
X that's the inner product
DX what is that anybody
remember Delta Delta i
j if I is equal to J they're the same
state the inner product is one
normalized state if they different
they're orthogonal corresponding let's
say to different energies sorry Delta i
j not zero Delta i
j that's another
fact now I'm going to show you another
uh a another little manipulation this
one yeah um why does the uh probability
density have that particular
form the
definition that goes back to the
postulates of quantum
mechanics the postulates of quantum
mechanics
um said that
probabilities here s of X this is the
inner product of s with a state
localized at X it's called the
probability amplitude the postulates of
quantum mechanics which I invite you to
go back to they're in the
book say that the square of that is the
probability
so okay here's a little
trick a little mathematical trick that
uh that occurs over and over
again take your orthonormal your
favorite orthonormal basis of functions
they could be signs they could be
cosiness they could be harmonic
oscillator wave functions whatever some
collection of size which are orthonormal
okay and if they're orthonormal and they
form a
basis then
if you take this object what is this
object this object is
a operator it operates on a state let's
see what it does let's let's just
explore what it does when it acts on a
state what does it do if it acts on a
state sigh then the beauty of the direct
notation is you can just take the
formula that you've written down here
when you act with this thing on a state
s with I is a number it's the inner
product of s with I time I that's what
it
does
uh now here's a fact about any
orthonormal
basis if you
sum of all elements of the orthonormal
basis in other words in this case all
the energy I vors up to
Infinity then what do you get
the unit operator I the identity
operator the operator that when it acts
on any Vector gives you back the same
Vector that's a marvelous theorem it's
in the uh it's in the in the
notes and you should go back to it don't
take my word for it you can even prove
it but it's a useful thing to
know okay let's use that now in the
following in the following way let's
take a project let's act with this thing
to the right and to the left what we're
going to do is we're going to
take and we're going to act what are we
going to act on we're going to act on a
state to the right which is localized at
position
X and on the left we're going to
act well actually what we're doing is
I'm taking the inner product of a state
with a particle at X with a state at
y everybody know what that the
mathematical symbol for that
is dist it's a direct Delta function but
let's come to that for a moment let's
not write that down yet let's write that
that is equal to the sumon
i
y i
x now all I've done is plug in the UN
operator here that does nothing but now
I have a formula here the inner product
of I with Y is s i of
Y let's see yeah the inner product of
any
state with an igen Vector position is
the um is the wave function of that
state here the state is I and it has
wave function SII of Y is over here s i
of
X and what does that have to equal it
has to equal Delta of x - y now
I sum over I is there yeah there
is
uh the second one yes the second
one I assume that's what you were asking
me yeah the star okay now we have a
marvelous theorem if we take take any
orthonormal basis they could be the igen
vectors of any Herm Mission operator but
in particular the energy and you
multiply for each one of those States s
star Time s and then some over them you
always get a Delta
function that's a good thing to know as
we'll
see it's useful it means there's many
many ways of writing a Delta function
just take any orthonormal basis and do
this these could be signs and cosiness
SS and
cosiness are another way of writing a
Delta function but
uh and this is the basic mathematics no
more mathematics tonight that's it I
think okay now let's come back let's
um let's go to the problem of studying
Min particles all at the same time
okay now how are we going to
characterize a State one set of states
which is particularly useful is a set of
states in which you say how many
particles there are with each one of
these energies for example how many
particles are there with State s One S 2
and S3 and so forth and so we can take
the multi-particle system and
characterize it by a basis of states
which are just N1 N2 dot dot dot n I dot
dot
dot the ends are the occupation numbers
they're the occupation numbers which
tell you how many particles are with
each energy level okay and those are
States they're not single particle
States they don't even belong in the
same Vector space with the single
particle wave functions the single
particle wave functions are themselves a
whole Vector space but we're now talking
about a bigger thing a bigger system and
so we should not confuse
the single particle states with the um
with the more General structures that
we're talking
about we use the same notation for them
because nobody ever invented a better
notation than thex bras and
cats but
uh okay next we would like to be able to
change the number of particles maybe we
do or maybe we don't want to change the
total toal number of
particles that not clear yet but we'd
like to be able to change them and so
we'd like to be able to raise and lower
the ends so we
introduce a oscillator for each eye for
each eye we introduce an oscillator and
at the moment this has nothing to do
with
oscillation this is just a trick this is
just a bookkeeping
trick although it will be more than that
later
for each one of these eyes we introduce
a creation operator or a uh a raising
operator let's call it a creation
operator since it's now going to create
a particle a creation operator and an
Annihilation
operator and the creation and
operators it's convenient to make them
just work exactly the same way as
harmonic oscillators it's just a
convenient way of uh dealing with them
a plus I and a minus I now I should tell
you right now that
um another convention for the same
things I'll write this in
red is to call this a dagger I that
looks like a plus
sign not quite but nevertheless same
thing and just calling this one AI
you'll often see it written that way
it's the same thing a dagger creates a
particle a does not but the uh the
correspondence is exactly
this
okay this space of states of the many
particle system is called Fox space
f FX was a Russian
physicist who somehow got his name
attached to this I don't really know
how
okay now we're going to find very con
very convenient and you'll see how it
works to introduce the notion of a field
operator the field operator has the same
symbol as the wave function s of X but
it's not a wave function it's not a wave
function it's not a state Vector for one
particle it's an operator and it's an
operator that acts on the space of
states of the mini particle
system it itself contains creation and
Annihilation
operators all right so let's write
the notion of a field
operator and the best way to motivate it
is to use it and see what it does now I
use a uppercase sigh I
hope I'm a little bit afraid that uh
that you won't be able to tell my upper
cases from my lower
cases all right that's that's an
uppercase s
right um its definition is the following
it's the sum of
I of let get it
straight the annihilation operator for a
particle in state I times the wave
function of a particle if it were in
state I and that's it summed over all
I now somebody asked me last week does
this have anything to do with Foria
transforms and you bet it does
if the wave functions here were the wave
functions of a free particle the igen
states of energy of a free particle in
not in a box just in a infinitely big
box what are those igen States those
igen wave
functions they're plain waves e to the I
KX and E to Theus I or e to the I PX and
E to Theus I PX so in that case if we
were using free particles in an
infinitely big box this would be an
expansion in SS and cosiness and those
A's would be the
coefficients of signs and cosiness they
would be the Foria coefficients of a
Foria expansion except that they're not
numbers they're
operators they're operators are things
that you measure or things that um that
play the role of operators in quantum
mechanics okay so that's one thing the
complex or the Herm Mission conjugate of
it
side Dagger of X this is of
X yeah what does it mean to say we have
an operator which depends on X well it
just means we have a different operator
at every X that's all we have a lot of
creation and Annihilation operators out
of them we can build a lot of
independent operators in fact we can
build an operator at each point x by
combining the A's with size of of X at
point x
so if we do this we make a different
operator at every
position and so we have a operator
function of
position okay or operate a valued
position it's complex or it's hermiss
conjugate is the same thing except
creation operators here this is a
uh I get so used
to yeah okay a
A+ Time s
dagger so s
star I of X now it doesn't
matter it's rather weird there were
notation some people use a notation
where this is called SI star and some
people use it one where this is called s
and they get all mixed up it uh these
are definitions and so you can do what
you want but here's the definition we
use as I said there are two operative
functions now neither one of these is a
herion
operator uh they have the creation
operators and Annihilation operators are
not her Mission their conjugates are
each other if you add them or if you add
them you make something that's her
Mission if you take any Herm Mission
operator sorry any operator and add it
to its Herm Mission conjugate it's Herm
Mission so if we add these two they
become Herm Mission and Herm Mission
means observable means something you can
measure in the
laboratory so the some of them is a
thing you could measure and the
difference is the difference or
Mission what happens if you take the
difference of of a of a number and its
complex
conjugate do you get something
real you get something pure imaginary
but if you multiply it by I then you get
something Herm Mission so
each the sum and difference of these
defin some Herm Mission uh observables
okay but right now we're not observing
them we're just going to use them as
bookkeeping
devices okay now let me show you another
interpretation of s of X what it
does in particular let's ask what it
does when it acts on the vacuum the
vacuum means a state with no particles
in it all and so the vacuum that's
called
vacuum which we usually denote just by o
is really the fox based state in which
all the occupation numbers are zero all
the same thing here
vacuum Fox Bas state with which all the
occupation numbers are zero sometimes
just called the vacuum or just called
the state
zero okay let's Act
yeah let's not act yet let's write down
the following
formula this is a one particle State Nel
one particle and only one
particle and let's write it in the
following form let's
use this anybody know what the name for
this kind of formula
is Project no it's not a uh well it is a
projector it's a trivial projection
operator it's it's one it's called a
resolution of the
identity it's a way of writing the unit
operator as a sum over a lot of uh um
orthogonal
vectors all right so let's let's plug in
the resolution of the identity Su on
i
i s i what is I I is a state in which
there's one part particle and only one
particle in the I energy level
here
okay what is this thing here this
is
sorry
x x sum of i x
i what is this object
let's go up to the top formula and you
see that when you project on to X you
get a wave function this here is s
star I of X it's the complex conjugate
of the wave function of the I energy
level the I energy level has a wave
function this is its complex
conjugate wave function itself would
have the opposite
order what about this state here that's
a state with one particle in the I
energy level so I'm going to write it
this way I'm going to take a creation
operator for making a particle in the I
energy and multiplying it by the
vacuum I've created one particle in the
state I by applying the creation
operator on the vacuum and that's
exactly the state here on the other hand
this is just a complex conjugate of the
wave function and my rule is sum
did I erase the defin no there's the
definition of the field
operator okay go to the second row
SAR the field operator is sum of I A
Plus of
I times the complex conjugate of the
wave function that's exactly what you
see here
right so this is exactly equal
to the field
operator at position X on the
vacuum that gives us a new
interpretation of s it's the operator
which creates out of the vacuum a
particle at position
I I think that's a fairly intuitive
thing that it's a Quantum operator
position at position X
sorry good so the a I create particles
with certain energy levels the P creates
particles at certain
locations it's also a kind of creation
operator the field operator itself is a
kind of creation operator but instead of
creating a particle with an energy with
a definite energy it creates a particle
with a definite position you want
dagg here yeah it should be star it
should be dagger good
you never use star for operators use
dagger good question this assumes that
the creation operator and wave
function
no yeah wave functions are
numbers they're numbers they're not
they're they're trivial operators
they're
numbers sometimes ordinary numbers are
called C numbers this was another
invention of d C stands for classical
just classical numbers operators he
called Q numbers for
Quantum
okay Q numbers don't always commute C
numbers always commute with themselves
but they also commute with everything
else because they're just
numbers okay so now we have a lovely new
interpretation of the field operator
it's the creation operator for a
particle at a point of space
let's look at some interesting
quantities I think with uh well well we
can put this
up just to get a little more experience
with this let's play with it a little
bit here's an
[Applause]
interesting here's an interesting
quantity integral
DX the operator s
Dagger of
x times s of X now is this the same
thing as up on the top of the Blackboard
up there the x s star of x s of x
no it's not the same thing it looks very
similar but it's not the same thing in
the top formulas up on top the size is
just wave functions one particle wave
functions they're not operators and the
right hand side is just one by total
probability this object here is an
operator Sai is an operator s dagger is
an operator when it acts on a state it
does something this one creates a
particle this one annihilates a particle
so but nevertheless it has some formal
structural similarity with the thing up
on top one wonders what is it does it
have some meaning is it uh is it
something uh that has a physical
significance is it something that you
can measure incidentally it's Herm
Mission because if you take any operator
and multiply it by its Herm Mission
conjugate the result is Herm Mission
that's like multiplying a uh complex
number by its complex conjugate the
result is always real
okay so let's see if we can figure out
what this thing
is First
Step let's replace the size by their
definitions so this is integral
DX and now size star that's a sum of
I it's going to get messy but then it'll
get easy
AI dagger or
ai+ times s star I of
X without H without without the
what without the
which no it's
right now I'm going to write the s that
has another separate sum not the sum
over the same I it's a sum over a
different I but I can just call J it's a
double sum there's a double sum here and
the double sum has
AJ s j of
X it looks a bit complicated an an
integral over an integral over X of a
double sum over I and
J plus the fact that the integral is
over all space and I and J go from 1 to
Infinity so if you want actually to
calculate it to put it on your computer
your computer would run forever and ever
and ever and ever and would never halt
uh however we can do better than that
let's do the integral over X first now I
think we have a formula here
um
uh s i
ofx there it is there it is right here s
i of X with s j that's just the
orthogonality relation so when I
integrate over x s dag Time s i just get
Delta i j that nice let's uh write it in
a simpler way this is
equal to we've done the integral sum
over I and
J A + I A
J times the chronica
delta in other words we get a term for
each I
where for each I and J except only when
I and J are equal and so this is equal
to the sum of
I of a dager i
AI what is a dag I * a i for a harmonic
oscillator it's just a number
operator the thing whose igen values are
the N the little
n this is the big in so so this can be
written as the sum of
I of the number operator for each one of
these
oscillators in other words it's just the
total number of particles the number of
particles in the first mode plus some
first wave functions plus the number of
particles in the second wave function
plus the number of particles in the
third wave function so what is this
thing it's an operator that represents
the total number of particles
for each one of these Fox States it's
just a sum of the little ends now
there's an infinite number of little
ends right there's N1 there's N2 there's
N3 is this not is this going to be a
finite number well remember that most of
those eyes correspond to very very high
energies if the St that we're talking
about is not dominated by insanely High
energies then these ends Must Fall Off
quickly the number of particles with
energies of a zillion zillion zillion
must be uh essentially zero so in order
that the total um energy be finite you
certainly have to have a total number of
particles
finite and this thing here is typically
finite notice it's formal similarity
with the integral SAR the integral s
star s was also the total number of
particles but only in the case where the
number of particles was known to be
one and that's just the accident the
total probability is one happens that
the total number of particles is one and
so that's up there but here exactly the
same formal looking structure is not
telling
us total probability it's telling us how
many particles we
have so if that's true then what
corresponds to the probability density
at a point of space the probability
density at a point of space why not just
the density of particles point of space
probability getes you want a function of
all of the X's of all the particles
right would
be right
right remember this is not okay the
answer to the question is this thing
here is the density of
particles Okay so we can write then
that why because its integral is a total
number of
particles now I'm not going to write
that it's a probability density I'm
going to write that it's a
density but the density is not
necessarily definite remember we're
doing quantum mechanics a thing can be
an observable but there are states
generally typical States the thing is
not going to have a definite value you
can measure it you can measure the
density of particles strictly speaking
you wouldn't measure the density of
particles in a point what would you
do you'd integrate over a little volume
and ask how many particles are in that
volume so if I integrate this over a
small volume not over all space that
tells me how many partic are in that
small volume I can measure it I won't
always get the same
answer I measure it in one state I
measure it in another state it's uh like
measuring any other quantum mechanical
variable you can get a variety of
answers and
um but this will tell you what the
number of particles is in a small volume
that's its role so it's it's a kind of
dens it is a density it's literally the
density of particles
a question yeah it's about the operators
as survi dagger and so
on is I mean in this formalism the you
they only operate on the state vectors
but not on the wave
functions not on the single particle
wave
functions right now let's come back for
a
moment this is not the most General
State that you can have this is a one of
a basis of states you can superpose
these just like in any Vector space you
can add vectors you can add vectors with
different numbers of
particles you can add uh even if you
have the same number of particles you
can add vectors in which there are five
particles here seven particles here you
can add that to another Vector where the
sevens and the fives are
interchanged 7 and five is 12 you could
add it together with a vector with 12
particles all at the same PL same ey
there are many
states uh and and super positions of
States many many possibilities in any
part whatever the state is
though the operator representing the
number of particles in a small
volume is s star s it's a thing that you
measure it's a thing that you measure
when you look in that small volume and
you ask how many particles are
there so although I haven't told you how
to measure Sai
itself siar SII is a is a is a familiar
thing it's just a number of particles in
a little volume question if you divide
this operator the top of their B in by
the number of particles would be fair to
interpret it as a probability density of
finding a particle at any particle at
pointex
position so now the look on your fa is
like yes but you don't like no it's okay
well you could say this volume has a
certain fraction of that volume
yeah no that's not the point supposing
you have a lot of particles even just
classically you have a lot of
particles and you want to know what's
the probability that any one particle is
in a little
volume well to a high approximation if
the number of particles are right all
you have to do is one
measurement measure how many particles
are in that small volume and divide by
the total number that's not the
definition of the probability and you
can get you know you could accidentally
get
zero you could accidentally get too many
most of the times within a margin of
error you will get the number of
particles being the probability for a
particle to be in there number of
particles divided by the number all
right so it's it's not an identity to
say that this thing when divide
appropriately divided by uh the total
it's not an identity to say that it is
the um is the probability for particle
to be in that
region the probability can
be a half have two regions of space
probability a half here and a half here
and you have a million particles okay
you could accidentally discover that all
the particles are on one side not very
likely but you could Discover it okay
you make that measurement and the answer
is a million on one side none on the
other side not equal to the
probabilities but most of the time
within the margin of error within about
a square root of the number of particles
you'll
get the
probability so that's the sense in which
I was a little waffling on whether you
want to call it the probability or not
this thing really stands for the measure
for the uh for the observable which
really corresponds to the number of
particles that you actually get when you
look in
there however yeah so what happens to
say of charge if you have a state with
one electron superposed with a state
with zero electrons yeah that's a bad
thing to
do right but what you could do no that
that normally doesn't occur but what you
could do is have a have a superposition
of states in which there's some number
of
electrons distributed throughout the
different states and then add that to
some number which is distributed
differently same number of electrons
photons however because they don't have
charge you have no problem superposing
different numbers of photons now even
with
electrons you can uh don't forget there
are other species of particles in the
world in particular there are
positrons okay so you can superpose
states with different number of
electrons and and positrons as long as
the total charge adds up to the same
number okay but right now we're just
inventing for ourselves the concept of a
Quantum
field all right let me do one more
little manipulation to show you another
example of um of things that you can
build I'm a little worried
[Applause]
um I I was going to start working out
the expression the operator made out of
the size which stands for the energy of
the whole
system
um we probably won't get quite there
tonight but let's uh let's
let's let's
begin here's what we found we found that
the integral of x of side Dag
was the same as the sum of the number of
particles in each uh that was what these
little manipulations did told us that
this is the same as
this now let's do a slightly different
thing let's
start with a formula for the total
energy now I'm interested now only in
systems with independent particles
particles are not interacting with each
other that's typically an approxim
it tends to work when the particles are
pretty dilute even photons if you make
them dense enough will start to interact
with each other and then the energy will
not just be the sum of the energies of
the photons now how dense do you have to
make them plenty dense much denser than
you can make in a
laboratory uh but still in
principle in Principle Energy is not
equal to the sums of the energies of all
the particles in the system but
typically if the particles are not too
dense and there aren't too many of them
per unit volume it's generally a good
approximation so let's take that
approximation and uh think of it now as
a principle of free particles free
particles particles that don't interact
with each other then what is the energy
the energy is the
sum over all modes mode means one of
these single particle W single particle
States it's the terminology mode mode
means a single particle State sum of I
of the number of
particles in that state times the energy
associated with that state okay we
called it last time Omega
I we could call it Omega H bar I but I'm
going to leave the har bar out for now
put it back
tomorrow Omega I and energy are the same
thing I just used
Omega because we're working with
oscillators but um but it is just the
energy of the I uh I
mode okay this is the energy of um of uh
we can also write
that as a sum of
I of a dagger
I AI time Omega I it looks a lot like
this over here the only difference each
is that each I is weighted with a factor
of Omega I what I want to do and I won't
do it tonight is to go from an
expression like this back to an
expression like this except for this
Beast over here what we're going to get
is something involving the field
operators and that thing that involves
the field operators is going to be the
energy of the fields it's going to be
the energy be the sum of all the
energies of all the particles but it's
going to be something that's expressed
in terms of the field operators and
we'll just call it the uh the energy of
the
field that's going to be something
reasonably
familiar uh but we won't do it tonight
tonight yeah
H Oh I thought it was uh fast it did go
fast I
was oh right right right
see if time is not invariant what's
happened
to the
energy
okay
okay I was wondering about
that okay we'll do a little more
then yeah
the no they're just the energies of the
eye State the wave functions are
functions of
position that's a function of position
but the energy that's associated with it
is just the energy of the first of the
ground state of the system of the ground
state of the one particle
State no the omegas are not functions of
position they're functions of I they're
functions of which energy level we're
talking
about
okay okay so what are the Omega I the
Omega I are the energy levels which are
the solutions of the Schrodinger
equation the time independent shringer
equation to find the energy levels of a
system you solve the Schrodinger
equation and you find out which igen
values on the right hand side of the
time independent shorting equation give
you
Solutions all right so let's write out
the time independent shring your
equation now we're going to write an
equation which determines the
omegas are we assuming that there are or
not interactions no no interactions you
w you weren't listening free particles
no
interactions right
so the answer is yes we
are are or
not no we are not assuming there are
interactions yes we are assuming there
are no
interactions or at least that we're in a
situation where interactions are very
unimportant particles too far from each
other
okay all right so what do we know about
Omega Omega is a solution of the time
independent shinger equation let's write
down the schinger equation the schinger
equation or the time independent
schinger equation of course it's just
now we're talking about the one particle
schinger equation the shinger equation
for only one
particle and what does it look like well
it's the one particle
hamiltonian acting on a wave function is
equal some
SI
I and it's equal to the igen value Omega
that's the energy level time
SII and what's the hamiltonian the
hamiltonian is let's just take the
simplest thing P ^2 over
2m plus a potential
energy the particles may be interacting
with a potential energy but we're not
going to let them interact with each
other so it could be electrons orbiting
the Sun when're not treating the sun
Quantum mechanically we are treating the
electrons Quantum mechanically but we're
taking the approximation that the
electrons don't interact with each other
they only interact with the
sun okay so um what do we write down for
H H is potential kinetic energy p^2 over
M plus v of
X where V is potential energy let me
write it a little clearer
multiplying s of
x equals Omega I and this is the I side
of X the I energy level is Omega s i of
X now this is an odd thing here what do
I mean p^2 over 2 m we know what V of X
time on S of X means that just means
multiply s of X by V of X where V is
some potential energy but what does this
thing mean p^2 over 2
[Music]
m yeah we use P = Min - i d by
DX and you can as homework put in the H
bars
there's of course a component for each
dimension of
space so this becomes px2 + p y^2 + pz
^2 this thing here
becomes well if I want to write it in
three-dimensional language it becomes D
squ which means second derivative with
respect to X plus with respect to Y with
respect to Z A minus sign because of the
I squares I * I gives us a minus sign
and we divide it by 2
m now this is the thing we know what to
do with this on S just differentiate s
twice it's just the sum of the second
derivatives in the various directions of
space plus v ofx s of
X Plus V of X let's put it all in one uh
in one
bracket plus v
ofx s
i equals Omega s i Omega I SI I Omega
depends on which energy level we're
talking
about well we're not going to solve any
shoing or equations tonight we're just
going to take omega I * SI I which
notice let's see does it no it hasn't
appeared yet um we're just going to use
the
formula when without solving it we're
going to use the formula without solving
it
okay I think the easiest way to get
there is to write down the answer and
then prove that the answer is the same
as this it's going to be the easiest way
to get there so let's put this up on
top I'm going to write down the answer
and then we're going to prove it's the
same as that
okay before I do let me point out
something about ordinary quantum
mechanics one particle quantum mechanics
supposing I wrote down the expression
integral
DX SAR of X any wave function whatever
times - d^ 2/ 2 m + v
ofx s of
X what would this thing be anybody
know it's the expectation value of the
energy it's the this is H
and this is basically sandwiching
H between bra and K vectors it's the
expectation value of the energy so
here's a formula for the expectation
value of the energy of one
particle what I'm going to tell you is
that the actual operator representing
the hamiltonian of the many particle
system can anybody guess from this what
the answer
is what's
that well no we know that
but I'm looking for another expression
for the same thing and I want to guess
at this point and then show it's the
same as
thatx what's that expand it as plus a
plus b and a minus B yeah we can do we
can do something like that but I can I
make a guess what did we do to go from
the um what did we do to go from
the probability to find a particle to
get to the number of particles in a
small region repl the size by the
operator indeed we just replaced the
little size by the big
size and that sort of gave us the sum
over all the
particles uh of sort of the same
question so let's try here's here's
here's a
guess no it's not a guess for me it
would be a guess for you except
uh of course it's not a guess
I remember learning about this when did
I learn about it 19 probably
1961 and I was kind of Blown Away this
this reading D's book I think reading
D's book this just blew me away that
this is the same as
this let's prove it let's go through the
steps the first thing to do is to
replace
S by um by the definitions up there so
let's replace S by the definitions this
becomes integral
DX now this one here is sum of
I
uh
AI
dagger SI I star of X right that's this
one over
here and this one over here is sum over
J
um so i j of x * A
J everybody happy with that a a minus J
I
guess that's all I did I plugged in the
formula this can be written as a sum of
I and J and replace the second summation
sign there just get rid of it and now
sandwich this minus d^
s over 2 M plus v
ofx now what the devil does this mean
for this to act on this object
here what does it mean well it simply
means that you do these operations on
ordinary wave functions this is an
ordinary wave function function we know
how to differentiate it we know how to
multiply it by V of X and so we have an
operation that we know how to
do we might not be able to do it because
it might be too complicated but we can
at least Define the
Operation this differentiates I twice
this multiplies by V but we already know
at least I hope we know somewhere on the
Blackboard here
nope Schrodinger equation here's the
shringer equation equation the Shing
equation tells us exactly what this
is- d^ 2 2m plus v of X acting on S just
gives us Omega I * I so we can
erase I don't like erasing I won't erase
we can write this integral DX sum of I
and J A + I let's group it together with
a minus J over there now there's s i
star of
X now there's this Beast multiplying s
that's just Omega
j s of
J what's the next
step Del integrate over
X integrate over X when you integrate
over X SAR x i * s j that's just chronic
Delta no that's just equal to sum of I
and
J A+ I A minus J Delta i
j but with one new factor that we didn't
have when we did the probability or we
did the just the counting of particles
Omega J and that's exactly
this we have a lovely expression
now this is the
energy of a field and it's given in
terms of something quadratic in the
field with a certain differential
operator what can you compare that with
in
electrodynamics in
electrodynamics very very similar kinds
of things or in any field Theory you
take the fields you differentiate them a
couple of times make a quadratic
expression and integrate over space
that's the characteristic um formula for
the integral for the energy of a field
all field theories have that property
that the energy is equal typically to um
to something quadratic in the field with
a couple of derivatives acting on the
fields the derivatives act on S here so
this is an example of the energy of a
field but it's also the
hamiltonian these things are energy
these things are operators the left hand
side is an operator it's not a number
it's an operator What operator well it's
a thing which has to do with the energy
it's the hamiltonian of the field
Theory okay it's the hamiltonian of the
field
Theory but it's also the
energy question
yeah most fundamental thing how did you
go from a multi particle system to a
field
right
there I went through every single
step in fact I belabored the steps no no
I went I followed all the steps but I
don't
see why this represents a f it's a
function of position that's all yeah
it's an observable or at least S Plus s
dagger is a quantum mechanical
observable
if you measure it at one place you can
measure it at the other place at the
same time you can uh so what more do you
want it's a function of position it's an
observable quantity that uh so we're
going to Define this thing because of
these properties it has might as well
call it a field mean mathematically it
is a field that's what you're saying
basically you can measure it it depends
on
position there is no other
definition now you could ask what field
is it the electromagnetic field no it's
not the electromagnetic field it stands
in the in the same relationship to the
electromagnetic field as photons would
be in a certain relationship to the
electromagnetic field whatever kind of
particles we're talking about here these
are non-relativistic particles they have
a mass they could be uh protons or
neutrons moving slowly they could be
electrons moving slowly as long as
they're not relativistic as long as the
energy is given by p^2 over 2 n
these this field is the field for those
particles those particles are the quanta
of that
field in the same precise sense that
photons are the Quant of the
electromagnetic field the
electromagnetic field would have an
expression for the energy it also has
two derivatives field
squared uh
and it's quite similar although not
identical excuse me you that white this
one
here
right okay so we've we've invented a
Quantum
field we've invented two observables one
of them is the particle density the
other is now
we have the energy but the energy is the
integral over a space of something what
would you call a thing uh that's being
integrated the energy density it's the
energy density so what's in here let's
get another color what's in here is the
energy density the local energy
density by measuring it and or
integrating it over a small volume you
find out how much energy is in that
small
volume so it's not integrated over all
space you could integrate it over all
space and it's a total
energy that's this but if we have
something and the total energy is equal
to an integral of it it stands to reason
or we can call that thing we
might we
uh it's a definition of the energy
density it's not the only definition
there's a little bit of ambiguity but um
question please um in that formula eal
Su n i Omega I capital N how is it
different from the little ends the
little ends are the igen values of the
big big is an operator little ends are
just
numbers oh
thank quick question syntax can you
express that field equation in terms of
well it's not a field equation yet I
mean yeah in terms of direct
notation because it's it's it's like
very analogous to what you have on the
upper
board which you can express in the you
know uh
uh carrot what direct carrot not
whatever it's called BR and cats yeah
Bret yeah no no no no but these are not
States these are
operators they don't they're not brasen
cats
the bras and cats these are the bras and
cats of the
system right but but but you expanded
the the to to do the uh little ends
that's really sort of an elaboration of
it um it's not officially what bracket
notation is really you said bracket
notation is a notation for a state
Vector of a system when you have the
little ends is not that's a state that's
a state it's a state with one N1
particles in the first state then
in this first yeah you have to learn to
separate the single particle quantum
mechanics from this multiparticle
quantum mechanics in this multi-particle
quantum mechanics there are things which
are operators which don't even occur in
the single
particle the
um right now this formalism or this
technology does allow you to recover
everything that we've ever said about
single particle quantum mechanics you
just go to the states in which the total
number of particles is
one okay and you work in that set of
States all of this formalism just
reproduces the physics of the single
particle quantum
mechanics but it allows you to deal with
any number of particles and in
particular there are states there are
states with large numbers of particles
typically
remember these are observables now
they're operators when there are a large
number of particles in the same state
then these size tend to behave very much
like classical
Fields um and we'll talk about that a
little more how is this connected to
classical field Theory well it's
connected to classical Theory like any
quantum mechanics is connected to its
classical uh to its classical U
counterpart for example expectation
values of things follow the same kinds
of equations of motion as the classical
equations of motion so you could ask for
example what happens to the expectation
values of SII SII is an operator it has
an expectation value at any
time we know the hamiltonian of the
system we can use it to work out the
time dependence of the state and then we
can use that to work out the time
dependence of the expectation value of
sign
guess what it essentially satisfies the
classical equations of motion of wave
Fields with the same classical
hamiltonian in fact it satisfies the
Schrodinger the time dependent
Schrodinger
equation so as I said this is a very
beautiful formalism it
is a bookkeeping device but it's also
the the fundamental connection between
particles and wave
Fields um and there is no other
connection this is it that's uh that's
the that's the
connection we'll explore it in a great
deal of uh of
um
exploration okay uh any yeah I've been
struggling with the manipulation of the
creation Annihilation operators inside
that integral you seem to treat them
almost like numbers where you can no I I
I I never switched that
I never commuted
them if I had commuted them and switched
that
order um yeah they're numbers they are
numbers here they are I'm sorry the size
are numbers the A's are
operators but when the okay so if the a
operates on a say the last pair
when
AJ minus operates on S side J it doesn't
operate on side J just no no it may
operate on some N1 N2 N3 and so forth he
took advantage of the fact that the size
are operate or numbers numbers and
because they're numbers you can pull out
the whole Delta function right and then
you're just left with the AIS and ajs
the only manipulation that you wouldn't
want to do freely without thinking about
it is to move an A minus past an A+ they
don't commute with each other that's
where the operator character of them
would come in but as far as moving them
past ordinary numbers that's fine the
derivatives here don't act on them the
derivatives act on the size
so uh there's
no cause to worry about any of the
operations I did there would be a cause
to worry if I to move a minus past A+
but we did interchange e IUS i+ but it
introduced a plus one in certain certain
things we do oh we do yeah I we just
have to be careful about it that's all
yeah yeah we didn't play some funny game
with
the but that's only these are only
derivatives acting on ordinary
functions I'm just saying we sort of
pulled it all out into a Delta
that's the integral over X right right
yeah so I mean I didn't say it wasn't
valid I'm just saying it was a little
that's a little trick that's a little
tricky what we did we couldn't do the
integral of x in this form what we did
was
say that this operation
here just multiplies s j by Omega once
it became Omega then we could do the
integral of x yep yeah right
so I didn't cheat you I didn't do
anything that uh that the that's just a
number just a number so you in Sher
formalism say treat operators as things
that can operate on functions on the way
functions what say that again in
Sher yeah operators can operate on Wave
functions they right just these in this
form and these operators just operate on
state pictures and not right you can
imagine how confused they were
in the early days before draak mastered
all of this and uh and put it together
they were very confused about the
meaning of the wave function some some
people thought it was a field that you
you know a real field like the
electromagnetic field some people
thought it was just an auxiliary device
for computing
probabilities and uh and if that's all
it was then what does it have to do with
the electromagnetic field and what's the
connect there were several different
ideas about what the connections between
particles and waves were on the one hand
the single particle wave function
satisfied a wave equation the
Schrodinger equation looked sort of
suspiciously like Maxwell's equations it
does roughly speaking not quite looks
like Maxwell's equations Maxwell's
equations were not equations as far as
anybody knew for um for Quantum
amplitudes they were equations for
measurable values of the field but still
there was some connection some funny
connection between these fields and
particles namely the field was made out
of Quant called photons so there was a
lot of Confusion And this is the uh the
resolution of that confusion
that I said for them
[Laughter]
may no no this is it that's it that's
all there is have some background in
cover spaces Vector spaces no I don't
think so so he just had well he made it
all up
himself which is fortunate because had
he used the the notations that were
there already you
know I taught quantum mechanics last
year for the in the mathematics
Department which was a lot of fun but
there was a crazy point at which I was
explaining their act notation and I told
them that every Vector we call the
we call these a vector space or whatever
s and the official
term the cats and the official
mathematical term for the bras is the
Dual Vector space it means complex
conjugate essentially the Dual Vector
space and I learned to say dual that
made them happy and then I said there's
an inner product between every vector
and its dual and they said no no no you
can't do that you cannot have an inner
product between a vector and its dual
you can only have an inner product
between a vector and itself and I said
look I'm telling you there's a just
trust me I know what I'm talking about
you can have an inner product between a
vector no no no illegal not allow not
allowed not allowed okay well of course
it turned out that the that they just
have a notation for the inner product of
two vectors take two
vectors and you put them next to each
other this way and then you put some
funny symbol around them like this and
that's the inner product between SII and
fi what is it equal to it's equal to SII
fi when they finally got the hang of
this the mathematics professors all said
wow this is powerful it makes everything
work simply for example they were again
blown away by this formula that I I is
equal to 1
and then all you have to do to multiply
it by a state is just do what it says
sign and this is the inpr they'd never
seen that
before right of course they saw of
course they've seen it they understood
it all completely but they had never
seen it in this compact notation
where you you almost can't make mistakes
anything you do turns out to be
right right so D was
clever he also he he you know if you ask
was his mind and ordinary mind it was
not he was probably Autistic or
something close to
it
yeah so he saw things in different
patterns than most of us
do going back to what you were saying a
little while ago about this elegant
formalism it's sort of begging the
question for me are Fields just for
ISM no you can measure them but are you
just measuring properties of collections
of particles yes but they're measuring
you're measuring partic properties that
you might not have guessed they're
not no you're not measuring the
properties of classical particles you're
measuring the properties of quantum
particles and Quantum particles have
properties like interference and that uh
the classical particles don't so yes
you're only dealing with a system of
particles that's
all but because they're quantum
mechanical they have kinds of properties
interference and entanglement and other
things which ordinary particles don't
have classical particles and this
accounts for all of
it is there some sort of identification
between uh for example let's say the
density of photons and the electrical
field strength yeah okay yeah well one
has to be a little bit careful when
you're dealing with relativistic
particles and I've been careful not to
deal with relativistic particles only
non-relativistic when you're dealing
with relativistic particles the notion
of the momentum of a particle is very
well defined the notion of a position of
a particle is not and if the notion of
the position of the particle is not
defined then the notion of the density
of particles is not defined but what is
defined is the density of energy and the
density of energy has a similar uh
form but you know if if I if we don't
split too many hairs then the square of
the electric field is qualitatively
related to the density of
photons so in relativity the you can
have a defined momentum but not so much
with position is that you're saying yeah
position is not a good concept in
relativistic uh systems yeah you can
even you can even make
um if you if you define this is not
especially useful but it's a fact if you
define a vector s out of the
electromagnetic
field you define it as the electric
field plus I * the magnetic field take
that
quantity size star now there now this is
there are three components to this so
it's not quite the same as this three
components electric
field minus I * a mag magnetic field
then SAR
Sai is not quite the density of photons
it's it's the energy density so it's the
density of photons weighted with the
energy of each Photon that's a good
concept for photons the the density of
photons itself is not a good concept so
SAR s is e^2 plus b^ s
if you know any electrodynamics you know
that E2 + b^2 is the um is the energy
density and um and S satisfies a uh a
shingle like
equation it's fun to work out from
Maxwell's equations what s and this is s
dagger if you know Maxwell's equations
you can work out the equations for S for
S and
uh it's a simple
equation simpler than Maxwell's
equations
themselves
okay uh I got got a question quick
question um energy equals the integral
of capital F dagger five it's well mean
I'm just abbreviating that side dagger
terms this differential operator here s
if you switch the S and the side dagger
does that have any meaning it's clearly
not you're not allowed to pass them
through each other without taking care
of the commutator right so it has a
meaning but it's just uh but it is what
it is it's is an IT corresponds to an
extra additive constant uh the ground
state energy it's uh right let's see if
we can make a guess I'm not going to try
to prove this it's easier than what I
did here and you can try it
um and for the single particle quantum
mechanics momentum p is equal to minus i
d by
DX there's some plunks constant in there
right what's the expectation value
supposing I have a single particle wave
function s of
X what's the average or the expectation
value of the
momentum well you take you take the C
Vector side you take the moment NM
operator and you sandwich it usual
sandwich to create the expectation value
what that means is you integrate overx
DX s
star times minus I DCI by
DX so let's put the minus I on the
outside
here so I star time d by the X and you
integrate it over all
space what about the momentum operator
not the expectation value of the
momentum but the momentum operator for
this field Theory do Fields have
momentum Fields have momentum if you
take electromagnetic beam from a laser
and you shine it on the wall if the uh
laser beam is powerful enough it'll blow
a hole in the wall why because it
carries a lot of momentum it exerts a
force on the wall
Fields have momentum classical Fields
Quantum fields in the quantum case the
field momentum is just the momentum of
all the photons okay so here we have a
expression for the average momentum of a
particle in quantum mechanics can you
guess what the expression for the total
momentum of all the particles
is yeah what
you Chang oper just replace the size by
size of bigger
size
sigh this is the operator that
represents the
momentum if you measure the momentum how
do you measure the momentum you see how
big a hole you blow in the wall by uh by
uh right you measure the momentum not
the average of the momentum the actual
momentum in a wave going by you how do
you measure it you see how hard it hits
you how much force it exerts on
something this is the operator the
observable that corresponds to that uh
to that this is the mathematical Herm
Mission operator that corresponds to
that
observable you can also calculate its
expectation value this is an observable
it is not the expectation value if you
give me a state I can calculate the
expect this is something okay this is
something we'll do we'll try next week
these are operators they have
expectation values they are not the
expectation values you need a state you
need an operator and a state to
construct an expectation value where's a
state give me a state well if you could
take those inst States up there N1 N2
N3 and uh calculate the expectation
value of the
momentum okay
um I think we'll finish for tonight
unless somebody has some good questions
because I've I've um I have not run out
of things to talk about but it's a
natural Breaking Point next time we'll
talk about processes in uh in particle
physics physics and how they're
represented by these
fields in a very simple context in a
very simple context we'll talk about
how field operators Implement processes
that take place when particles Decay
when particles scatter and so
forth for more please visit us at
stanford.edu